<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The svvord-bearer, or, Magistrates charge a sermon preached in the Chappell of Guild-Hall, at the election of the Lord Mayor / by Mathias Milward ...</title>
            <author>Milward, Matthias, fl. 1603-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50961</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2187</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14639</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12939862</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12939862</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95845</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50961)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95845)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 989:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The svvord-bearer, or, Magistrates charge a sermon preached in the Chappell of Guild-Hall, at the election of the Lord Mayor / by Mathias Milward ...</title>
                  <author>Milward, Matthias, fl. 1603-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 22, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Norton for Samuel Man ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>16[41]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Mayors --  England --  London --  Election.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95845:1"/>
            <p>THE SVVORD-BEARER, <hi>OR,</hi> MAGISTRATES CHARGE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Sermon preached in the Chappell of GUILD-HALL, at the Election of, the LORD
MAYOR.</p>
            <p>By MATHIAS MILWARD, Bachelor of Divinitie, Miniſter of Saint HILLENS.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>AUG. To. 8. Pſ. 84.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Juſtitia &amp; pax duae amicae ſunt, ſimul oſculantur; tu fortè unam vis, alteram
non facis.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>John Norton</hi> for SAMUEL MAN, dwelling at the Swan in Saint
<hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:95845:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95845:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR HENRY GARWAY KNIGHT, LORD MAJOR OF THE HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE CITIE OF
LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon of right belongeth to you, being by your appointment Preacht; as therefore rivers
runne to the ſea from whence they flow; ſo this returnes to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour from whence it
ſprang. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, It is yours (my Lord) by a due debt for many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours received, for which,
having no other way to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe my thankfulneſſe, I commend this poore ſervice of
<pb facs="tcp:95845:3"/>a verball but hearty acknowledgement for reall cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies. Lastly, your wiſe
wielding of the Sword you have borne, having drawne the hearts and voyces of the beſt towards
you, hath alſo induced mee to this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication; wherein as others may ſee what you have been,
ſo your worthy Succeſſour may ſee what he ſhould be; It was once mine, it is now yours,
and ſo is</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Honours moſt obliged,
Mathias Milward.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95845:3"/>
            <head>THE SWORD-BEARER OR MAGISTRATES CHARGE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 13.4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For he beareth not the Sword in vaine.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle here ſetteth downe a Rule for two ſorts of men; the Magiſtrate, and People;
teaching the one how to governe, the other how to obey. Now, the Magiſtrate muſt be the
ſubject of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe at this time; In whom two things are conſiderable. 1.
<hi>Honos,</hi> his Honour. 2. <hi>Onus,</hi> his Charge; his Dignity, and his Dutie. <hi>He
beareth the Sword,</hi> there's his honour: the <hi>Sword</hi> is a type of his authority: <hi>not
in vaine,</hi> that points at his office, not onely for pomp, or ſtate, but for uſe, for
execution of juſtice. In handling whereof, I would not be thought preſumptuous, as if like old
do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Phormio,</hi> I would teach <hi>Hannibal;</hi> for I profeſſe my
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95845:4"/>ſelfe <hi>exiſtimatorem, non magiſtrum,</hi> an Adviſer only, no
peremptory teacher; Neither let the name of <hi>Sword</hi> in theſe buiſie times be
prejudicious to what I ſhall ſay, and think not my Sermon the ſharper for that; for I ſhall
handle it ſo tenderly, as neither to provoke any enemies, nor to offend any friends, nor to hurt
my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore the Honor of a Magiſtrate ſtands in two things. 1. His Ordinance. 2. His
Preheminence.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> His Ordinance is of God; <hi>The powers that be, are ordained of God,</hi>
ſaith the Apoſtle; <hi>Submit your ſelves</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>to every
ordinance of man, for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as ſupreame, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
Governours, as unto them that are ſent by him.</hi> 1 <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 2.13. Saint <hi>Peter</hi>
calls them an humane ordinance, not in regard of the firſt inſtitution of it, but for uſe. 1.
<hi>ſubjectvè,</hi> becauſe it is executed by man. 2. <hi>objectivè,</hi>
becauſe humane affaires are the object of it. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in reſpect of the end,
becauſe ordained for mans good: yet the Originall is from God. For as in the Creation of the
world there was a ſpirit that formed; ſo in the conſervation thereof, the ſame ſpirit
reformeth to this day, and that's done by Ruling. Man being by nature a ſociable creature, take
away Rule and Power, you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe mans nature; and though ſinne brought into the world ſervitude
and ſlavery, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.25. <hi>Curſed be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, a ſervant of ſervants ſhall hee
be:</hi> yet God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ordain'd power and order; there's order among the bleſſed Angels,
if not <hi>ex praecepto</hi> yet <hi>ex conſilio:</hi> and in every man God hath imprinted a
double juriſdiction: one of the ſoule over the body, that's <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
of a Maſter: another of the reaſon over the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95845:4"/>petite: and that's <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the power of a Soveraigne. God in the
beginning gave unto man a three-fold pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; Firſt, over himſelfe, by free-will to govern his
acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for God ſet man at firſt <hi>non in Tuto ſed in cauto,</hi> ſaith S.
<hi>Bern.</hi> not in ſuch ſecurity that he could not fall, nor in ſuch neceſſity that he
could not chuſe but fall; but left him to the liberty of his owne will, not to fall if hee would
not offend, nor to offend unleſſe hee would him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. God gave him <hi>poſſe non
peccare,</hi> but not <hi>non poſſe pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care;</hi> that is, it was poſſible for him not to
ſinne, but it was not impoſsible for him to ſinne. The ſecond power was over the creatures;
for to mans <hi>multiplicamini</hi> God added <hi>dominamini. Let him have dominion over the fiſh
of the ſea, and the fowles of the ayre. Geneſis</hi> 1.26. The third power was over man; which
is either Oeconomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call in families, of the husband over the wife, father over his children,
maſter over ſervants; or Politicall in Citties <hi>viz.</hi> Monarchicall of one,
Ariſtocraticall of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny &amp; thoſe the beſt; or Democraticall which is the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular
ſtate; All were ordain'd of God either mediatly, or immediatly. <hi>There is no power but of
God,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; <hi>Non dicit, poteſtas eſt a deo, ſed non eſt poteſtas
niſi à deo,</hi> ſaith <hi>Muſculus;</hi> yea that of the devill, whoſe will though
it be ever wicked, yet his power by Gods permiſsion is never unjuſt; hee is called therefore
<hi>The evill ſpirit from the Lord.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.23. An evill ſpirit, ſaith S.
<hi>Gregory, Per deſiderium voluntatis iniquae,</hi> but yet from the Lord, <hi>per licentiam
poteſtatis juſtae.</hi> Sometime perhaps, <hi>Potens</hi> the Ruler is not of God,
<hi>Oſee</hi> 8.4. <hi>They have reigned, and not by mee.</hi> Or the manner of getting Rule is
not of God; for many runne <hi>ad Cathedram non ad Curam,</hi> to the chaire, not to the cure; and
<hi>Simon Magus</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:95845:5"/>will give any thing to be <hi>Simon Magnus;</hi> but the power it ſelfe is of
God. The bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> in her ſong ſaith, <hi>depoſuit potentes,</hi> Hee
hath put downe the mighty from their ſeat; not <hi>poteſtatem,</hi> power ſimply, but their
power, from doing further miſchiefe. The Elders gave glory <hi>ſedenti ſuper thronum,
Revel.</hi> 4. and caſt their crownes at his feet; for <hi>ego ſum qui transfero regna,</hi>
ſaith God in <hi>Daniel.</hi> All earthly power is but tranſlated, &amp; God is the Originall.
He that ſaid, <hi>Per me reges regnant,</hi> By me Kings reigne, ſaid alſo, <hi>et domini
dominantur,</hi> and Lords rule: It is the Lord that putteth the Sword into your hand. <hi>For he
beareth the Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond point is their Preeminence. Every where the Scripture ſtiles
them honourable. The King of Tyre is called the <hi>anoynted Cherub,</hi> whom God ſet in honour,
<hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.14. <hi>Deborah</hi> a Mother in Iſrael <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.7. They cryed before
<hi>Ioſeph Abrech,</hi> Bow the knee, or tender Father, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45. For as
<hi>Xenophon</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a good Ruler differs not from a good father. They
be called Heads, <hi>Numb.</hi> 1.16. for three cauſes. 1. For their eminence above the reſt.
2. For command, becauſe the head governes all the body; yea many times when the body is at
reſt, the head is moſt diſquieted. 3. For neceſſary uſe, becauſe from thence flowes
ſence and motion into all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body. And all theſe titles, what are they, but
obligations of greateſt duties, and of greater neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſity to depend upon God, both for advice
in wiſedome and aſsiſtance in power? But that which tranſcends all, is, <hi>I ſaid yee
are Gods;</hi> which is to be underſtood onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatively, becauſe God hath given them
power to ſpeake to the people in his name, and execute his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95845:5"/>
               <hi>I have made thee Pharaohs God,</hi> ſaid God to <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi>
7.1. And theſe attributes of honour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them how to governe, and others how to reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
them. Them how to governe, to rule for God, reward for God, puniſh for God; remembring alwaies
though they are gods of the earth, yet they are but earthen gods; In their greateſt glory they
are but <hi>virtus in infirmitate;</hi> and although by their birth or fortune they be ſifted
from the branne of the vulgar, yet they are but <hi>ejuſdem farinae,</hi> of the ſame meale.
Their heads of gold, and breaſts of ſilver, &amp;c. ſtand but upon feet of clay; the
ſplendour of their renowne, the glory of their riches, and ſtrength of their greatneſſe
hath but a duſty foundation; <hi>pulvis es, et in pulverem reverteris.</hi> Againe, it teacheth
others how to reverence them. <hi>They that rule well, are worthy of double honour,</hi> 1
<hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. Single honour howſoever, becauſe of Rule, which is Gods ordinance; but
<hi>double honour,</hi> if he be a good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, becauſe of his diligence.
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> very much honour; or <hi>double,</hi>
ſaith <hi>Aquine, reverentiae &amp; ſubſidij,</hi> reverence and maintenance, allegeance and
allowance. So tender is God for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of their dignities, that hee gave his people
charge, <hi>Elobim lo thikkallel, Thou ſhalt not raile upon the gods, nor curſe the Ruler of
thy people, Exod.</hi> 22.28. And by an ancient Canon, a ſevere Cenſure was impoſed upon him
that was <hi>contumelioſus in magiſtratum;</hi> if a lay man, to excommunicate him; if in
orders, to depoſe him; their perſons ſhould be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, inviolable, for they are
ſacred, like an <hi>Aſylum,</hi> a Sanctuary or conſecrated Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which for the veneration
of Religion might not be violated. For this cauſe <hi>David</hi> would not lay hands
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95845:6"/>upon <hi>Saul</hi> when occaſion gave him power over his life; for though hee
was wicked, yet hee was the Lords anoynted; he had <hi>ſanctitatem unctionis,</hi> though not
<hi>vitae;</hi> an holy calling, though not an holy carriage. S. <hi>Jude</hi> ſets it downe for
a note of reprobate men, <hi>to deſpiſe dominion, and ſpeake evill of dignities.</hi> Yet
ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious brood there is in the world, that bend their tongues like a bow againſt
authority, and ſhoot out their arrowes, even bitter words. What learned Praelate hath not this
Blatant beaſt bitten? what Reverend Judge hath not this ſerpent ſtung? What honeſt man hath
not been beſpattered with this filthy vomit? yea, Chriſt himſelfe was not free from the
aſperſion of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous ſpeakers, who called him a friend of Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and ſinners, and
aſcribed their miracles to the power of Belzebub. But let them goe; and <hi>good luck have you
with your honour; ride on becauſe of the word of truth;</hi> remember it is that which gives you
honour, and it ſtands with your honour to maintaine that. For you beare the <hi>ſword;</hi> And
ſo I take my leave of your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and come next to your charge; for as I have ſhewed them how
great they are, ſo I muſt needs tell them how good they ſhould be.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Their charge ſtandeth in the uſe of the <hi>ſword,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto three
things are required: 1. Good lawes, they are like the ſword in the ſcabbard. 2. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright
judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to thoſe lawes, that's like a ſword drawne. 3. Juſt execution, that
ſtrikes the ſtroke.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> To the making of good lawes three things are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. 1. The matter, which
muſt be agreeable to the law of nature and will of God. 2. The end, to maintaine vertue, and
ſuppreſſe vice. 3. Their extent, not for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95845:6"/>gaine, but for publick good. And when lawes are made, there's no exemption of any
perſon from their obedience and ſubjection. <hi>Let every ſoule be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the higher
powers,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. <hi>Omnis ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma; anima propter voluntatem, omnis propter
univerſalitatem;</hi> the ſoule, becauſe obedience ought to be voluntary; every ſoule
becauſe it muſt univerſall. To ſay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Clergie is exempted, becauſe it is not
ſaid <hi>Omnis ſpiritus,</hi> but <hi>omnis anima,</hi> that is, <hi>animalis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo</hi> the
laity, not <hi>ſpiritualis homo</hi> the Clergie, is <hi>vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rina gloſsa,</hi> and cates out
the bowels of the text. For the ſoule is taken for the whole man; <hi>every ſoule,</hi> that
is, every man; there were <hi>eight ſoules</hi> in <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark, that is, eight perſons,
1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.20. But I grant you ſaith <hi>Bellarmine:</hi> they are ſubject
<hi>obligatione directiva, non coactiva,</hi> by obligation of direction, not coercion, which is as
much as to ſay as farre as they liſt themſelves. Is this ſubjection, or rather is it not a
cunning evaſion? that's no law that hath onely reference to their diſcereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for whom it is
enacted; that very reference loſeth the reverence and authority of it. Juſtice and right in
giving every one his due, ſhould have the ſame place in the common-wealth, which faith and
religion claymeth in the Church. Now, as in religion there are ſome things in ſubſtance, and
ſome things of ceremony; ſo there are ſome points eſſentiall in juſtice, and ſome
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentall; the eſſentiall points of juſtice are the ſame in lawes of all common-wealths;
for what is a law but a divine ordinance, commanding things honeſt, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding the contrary?
The accidentall parts doe and may vary according to the circumſtances of times, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and
places. For as good remedies are occaſioned
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95845:7"/>from bad diſeaſes, ſo <hi>ex malis moribus bonae leges oriuntur.</hi> There
was in ancient times no law againſt a Parricide, whereof <hi>Solon</hi> being ask'd the reaſon,
anſwered, Hee thought no man ſo unnaturall as to commit that ſinne; but when the
wickedneſſe of the times had produc'd ſuch monſtrous Imps that did kill their owne fathers,
then a law was provided, and a puniſhment ſet downe; for the Party ſo offending, was to be
ſowed in a leathern ſack, with a Dogge, a Cock, a Viper, and an Ape, foure angry creatures, and
ſo caſt into ſome deepe water, as unworthy to reape the benefit of any of the foure
ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; the reaſon whereof is given to be this, <hi>Vt qui eum necaſſet unde ipſe natus
eſſet, careret rebus omnibus unde omnia naſcuntur,</hi> That he which kill'd him of whom he
was borne, ſhould be deprived of thoſe things whereof all things are bred. In the time of
Innocencie God gave man a law; One tree he muſt not eate of. It was not envie as the devill would
perſwade, but a type of <hi>Adams</hi> obedience, as if God ſhould tell him, ſaith Saint
<hi>Auſtin:</hi> If <hi>Adam</hi> would know the reaſon, <hi>Quia ego domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, tu ſervus;
obedientem te volo, non contradicentem,</hi> I am thy Lord, thou my ſervant; I will have thee
obedient, not repugnant. Much more now are lawes neceſſarie, yea new lawes according to
occaſion, either for preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſtop a miſchiefe enſuing, or for ſubvention to remedy
evils paſt. They are like waters that receive their tincture and taſts from the ſoyles
through which they runne, and ſo change according to the regions and governments where they are
planted; yet they proceed from the ſame fountaine of juſtice; They ought not by multitude of
conſtitutions to be ſnares to good minds, nor by the quirks of mercenarie wits to be perverted
to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95845:7"/>bad purpoſes; Lawes ſhould command, not diſpute. The people of
<hi>Aegina</hi> did impoſe a pecuniarie mulct upon him that had occaſioned a new Law. Amongſt
the Athenians there was but one new Law made for an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, and that was procured by one
that was <hi>monoculus,</hi> and the Law was this, That hee ſhould loſe both his eyes, who had
put out his that had but one. For our part (God be thanked) wee have good Lawes, no Kingdome
better; and whether there be any need of more, that muſt be left to the wiſdom of the
Eſtates. If I have herein exceeded my bounds, I cry pardon of the Lawyers; I am ſure the
leſſe wee have to doe with their Law, the better men will like of our Divinity. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with old
father <hi>Latimer,</hi> I hope it is no harme to wiſh one Law more to be made, which might be
like that of the Medes and Perſians unalterable, namely for execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe Lawes that are
to be made: For Lawes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made and not executed, are like the Sword in the ſcabbard. I come
therefore to the ſecond point, which is, the Sword drawne, and that's upright judgement.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> To cleare this paſſage, foure obſtacles muſt be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; Feare,
Covetouſneſſe, Hatred, and Favour; Feare dares not draw the Sword, Covetouſneſſe will
not, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred muſt not, and Favour may not: of each of theſe ſome thing.</p>
            <p>Feare was <hi>Pilats</hi> fault; hee ſought many meanes to deliver Jeſus, but feare of
<hi>Caeſars</hi> diſpleaſure hindered him: <hi>If thou let this man goe, thou art not
Caeſars friend,</hi> ſaid the Jewes; then he condemned Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 19.12. If he had
ſaid, <hi>Vivat Rex, &amp; currat Lex,</hi> God bleſſe <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and let the Law
have his courſe, he had beene a good Judge.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:95845:8"/>
            <p>There is a Signe in Heaven called <hi>Virgo,</hi> betwixt <hi>Leo</hi> and <hi>Libra;
Pierius</hi> in his Hieroglyphicks compares Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to this Signe: for Juſtice is a pure
intemerate Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, never corrupted by thoſe too ſhameleſſe Sollicitors, <hi>Nimium &amp;
Parum,</hi> Exceſſe and Defect: ſhee hath <hi>Leo</hi> on the one ſide, becauſe a
<hi>juſt man is bold as a Lion, Prov.</hi> 26.1. and <hi>Libra,</hi> a paire of Ballances, on the
other ſide, weighing out to every man his right; which he cannot doe equally, if he feare any
mans diſpleaſure. He muſt remember Gods encouragement to <hi>Joſua, Be valiant and of a
good courage.</hi> Feare is forbidden by our Saviour Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>Feare not them
that can kill the Body.</hi> A three-fold reaſon is there given; firſt, in regard of mans
impotence, for his power reacheth no further than the Body, which is but the Bellowes of the Soule,
through which ſhe breathes. <hi>Anaxarchi follem tundis, non Anax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archum,</hi> ſaid he, when he
was maul'd to death. Secondly, in regard of Gods providence, which extendeth it ſelfe to the
lives of unreaſonable creatures, without which a Sparrow falls not upon the ground. If the life
of a Sparrow be governed by Divine Providence, the price whereof is not a farthing; ſhall not the
life of the Juſt much more, the price whereof is the blood of Chriſt? Thirdly, whatſoever
becomes of our Bodies, not an haire ſhall be miſſing, at the Reſurrection: <hi>The haires
of your head are numbred,</hi> ſaith Chriſt. <hi>Non eſt timendum de majoribus ubi eſt cura
de minimis; ſi ſic cuſtodiuntur ſuperflua tua, in quanta ſecuritate eſt anima tua?</hi>
If God care for our ſuperfluities, much more for our neceſſaries, the Soule eſpecially.
<hi>Feare not therefore,</hi> ſaith our Saviour Chriſt. The Magiſtrate that beares the Sword,
muſt be magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous. Certainely, God hath ſet ſuch an impreſſion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95845:8"/>of Majeſtie in the face of lawfull Authoritie, that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe is
confounded in it ſelfe to behold it: For, if from hence the Power that is viſible, were not
more feared than the inviſible God, the world would be over-run with outrage. Therefore a good
Magiſtrate, like a wiſe Phyſician, feares not to let out the corrupt blood of Malefactors, to
ſave the life of the State; for the Body of the Common-wealth cannot live, unleſſe her bad
Members bleed: This requireth fortitude, and Feare dares not draw the Sword.</p>
            <p>The ſecond impediment, is Covetouſneſſe; and that will not draw the Sword. The Prophet
<hi>Oſee</hi> complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, <hi>Their Rulers love to ſay with ſhame, Bring yee, Oſ.</hi>
4.18. It was the fault of <hi>Samuels</hi> ſonnes, they did not walke in their fathers wayes: Why
ſo? <hi>Dilexerunt munera,</hi> they loved Gifts, nay, Bribes, that was the right name: What
followed? <hi>Perverterunt judicium,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.3. Then God tooke away the Government;
the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple choſe <hi>Saul</hi> King, and thoſe bribing Judges were caſt off.
<hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> jeaſting upon <hi>Cleon,</hi> as <hi>Plutarch</hi> hath it, ſaith,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, This man can skill of no ſtraine but the <hi>Dorick;</hi> alluding to
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neribus corrumpi,</hi> the bribing ſtraine, rightly ſo called:
for, <hi>a wicked man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>taketh a gift out of the boſome, to
wreſt or ſtraine the wayes of Judgement.</hi> Many a heavie Curſe hath God layd upon this
ſinne: <hi>Woe be unto them</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi>) <hi>that joyne houſe to
houſe, and field to field, till there be no place, Eſ.</hi> 5.8. not ſpeaking againſt
honeſt purchaſing, but wicked compaſsing, till there be no place, no place for a neighbour to
live by them. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> complained in his time of ſuch greedie encroachments: Rich
men cannot dwell alone
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95845:9"/>upon earth, ſayes hee; beaſts herd together, birds flock together, fiſhes
ſwim in ſholes together, <hi>nec dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ducunt ſed commercium vivendi,</hi> They finde a
kinde of commerce, no dammage in it; <hi>Solus tu homo conſortem excludis, includis feras,
ſtruis habitacula beſtiarum, deſtruis hominem,</hi> Man alone ſhuts out the companion of
his life, and emparketh beaſts.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Alexander</hi> ſent <hi>Phocion</hi> an hundred talents, he asked why amongſt ſo
many Athenians the King ſent gifts unto him? becauſe (ſaith the Meſſenger) he heares that
thou onely art a juſt man; then <hi>Phocion; Quin igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur poſthac me bonum eſſe
permittat,</hi> Let him ſuffer mee to be ſo ſtill, for this is the way to make me ſtark
naught.</p>
            <p>What is the glory of a Citie? not ſumptuous build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and ſtately pallaces, but where the
three faire daughters of <hi>Themis</hi> doe flouriſh, <hi>Eunomia, Dice, Eirene,</hi> Equity,
Juſtice, and Peace. Or as <hi>Perſa</hi> the Captive virgin ſaid of <hi>Athens,</hi> being
asked, if it were not a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrong fenced Citie, anſwered, <hi>Si incolae bene ſint
mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rati, pulchre munitam arbitror; perfidia &amp; peculatus ex urbe &amp; avaritia ſi
exulant;</hi> if perfidiouſneſſe, and perjurie, and falſhood, if ambition, and pilling, and
polling were baniſhed, it were then a goodly Citie indeed.</p>
            <p>When at a Diet in <hi>Wormes</hi> in <hi>Maximilians</hi> time, the Princes there met, and upon
occaſion ſet forth the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of their ſeverall Dominions;The Duke of <hi>Saxonie</hi>
glorying in his Minerall veines, The <hi>Bavarian</hi> in his beautifull Cities, The Count
<hi>Palatine</hi> in his fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile ſoyle: Onely <hi>Eberhard</hi> Duke of <hi>Wittenburgh</hi>
ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but this, I can boaſt of nothing in that kinde, but this I am proud of, I can lay
downe my head and ſleepe ſecurely in the boſome of any of my Subjects; an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuable
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95845:9"/>prerogative of a Prince, and no where to be found but where the Magiſtrate and
the people hate Covetouſneſſe. For as Feare dares not draw the Sword, ſo
Covetouſneſſe will not.</p>
            <p>The third impediment is Hatred; and that muſt not. For <hi>the wrath of man doth not
accompliſh the righteouſneſſe of God, James</hi> 1.20. For although it be ſaid at the end
of this verſe, that the Magiſtrate is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>muſt take vengeance in
wrath,</hi> or <hi>is a Revenger to execute wrath,</hi> that is, puniſhment <hi>upon him that
doth evill;</hi> yet he muſt not draw the <hi>ſword</hi> in anger againſt the Perſon, but
againſt the ſinne. There is a time when a man may be angry; <hi>Moſes</hi> was angry
againſt the Iſraelites idolatry, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.19. and did not offend; <hi>Jonas</hi> was
angry at Gods mercy in ſparing the Ninivites, and he was reproved; <hi>Doeſt thou well to be
angry, ſaith God, Jon.</hi> 4.4. Chriſt was rail'd at, mock'd, and crucified; yet was not
angry, but prayed for his enemies, <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they doe.</hi>
But when hee ſaw his Fathers Houſe abus'd, then he was angry, and whipt them out of the Temple;
hee had anger certainly, though not as a paſſion of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, yet of deteſtation; it was
zealous anger, not vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious anger. Unbridled anger is a temporary frenzie; for there's a two-fold
madneſſe; one of the head which makes men runne out of their wits; another of the heart which
turns them out of their patience, and that's anger. This if it be of long continuance, growes to be
hatred, and <hi>he that hates his brother, is a man-ſlayer,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.15. Not ſo
much becauſe he hurts his brother, whom he hates; but becauſe he ſlayeth his own ſoule;
yea, and his brothers too, if he could; <hi>Ille vivit,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine, &amp;
tamen tu occidiſti;</hi> hee liveth, yet thou haſt kill'd him
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95845:10"/>as much as in thee lyeth.</p>
            <p>Now, if a Magiſtrate be drawne into hatred of any mans perſon, hee may be a double Homicide;
for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the miſchiefe he doth to himſelfe, hee may be the death of another. When
<hi>Joſua</hi> proceeded againſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chan,</hi> he did it mildly; <hi>My ſonne,
confeſſe thy fault and give glory to God, Ioſ.</hi> 7.19. A Magiſtrate ſhould have
leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in himſelfe. <hi>Ariſtides</hi> ſitting in judgement upon two men that
were adverſaries, One of them thinking to make his cauſe the better by accuſing his enemie,
ſaid, O <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> this man hath done thee great wrong. My friend, quoth
<hi>Ariſtides,</hi> Tell mee what wrong hee hath done thee: for I ſit here to doe thee
juſtice, and not my ſelfe. This <hi>ſword</hi> therefore muſt not be drawne againſt the
perſon of the offender, but againſt the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the perſon; in deteſtation of the
fault, not of the man; for it muſt not be drawne in hatred.</p>
            <p>The fourth impediment, is Partialitie or favour. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſaphat</hi> having ſet Judges in
the Land, gave them this Charge; <hi>Take heed what yee doe, for you judge not for man, but for the
Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. That word excludes all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: for if he be puſillanimous,
he will judge for man; that makes him feare his enemies; if partiall, to favour his friends; if
covetous, to love himſelfe too much; if he be malicious, he will hate others: And then Truth
muſt needs have a cold Suit, when Malice is chiefe Juror, and Partialitie the Judge. I know Pitie
is the beſt prayſe of humanitie, and fruit of Chriſtian love; but in Judgement, it may have
no place: he muſt heare the ſmall as well as the great, the rich and the wretch both alike.
<hi>Alexander</hi> when he ſate in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, would with one eare open heare the Plaintiffe, and

<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95845:10"/>keepe the other for the Defendant: it was juſtly done; for, <hi>Qui ſtatuit
aliquid parte inauditâ alterâ, aequum licet ſtatuerit, haud aequus fuit,</hi> ſaid
the Tragedian. Hee that determineth upon hearing of but one party, though his judgement be true,
yet he is not right Judge. For favour being the falſe advocate of the gracious, is injurious to
truth; and it is required, that Judges ſhould be <hi>men of truth, Exod.</hi> 18. Now, there is
<hi>veritas vitae, veritas juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, veritas doctrinae;</hi> Truth of life, when our
converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is framed according to the rule of truth; truth of doctrine, diſtinguiſhing
truth from error, and right from wrong; truth of juſtice, in giving every man his owne. A
Magiſtrate therefore muſt be inflexible, unpartiall, free from paſſion and affection; with
a ſword in one hand, and his ballance in the other; <hi>Ponderat haec cauſas, percutit ille
reos;</hi> to ponder mens cauſes, and puniſh their offences, without partiality.</p>
            <p>Now having removed the impediments, I come to the drawing of the Sword, which is upright
Judgement. You will ſay, perhaps, it hath beene long in drawing: and I anſwer, The blocks in
the way were heavie, and not ſoone removed; and beſides, <hi>Nulla unquam de vita hominis
cunctatio longa eſt,</hi> a man cannot demurre too much upon a mans life: for, if he wrongfully
miſcarry, and the Sword be drawne unjuſtly, what amends can be made for his unjuſt
ſuffering? Upright Judgement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, according to Law, is the true drawing of the Sword:
whereunto three things are required; firſt, Wiſdome; ſecondly, Pietie; thirdly,
Juſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Wiſedome in diſcuſſing cauſes. This hath ever car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried that ſhew of
excellencie, that the very wicked have laboured to put on the vizard of it. <hi>Come,</hi> ſayes
<hi>Pharaoh,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95845:11"/>let us doe wiſely;</hi> yet his wiſedome proved folly, becauſe it was
againſt Gods people: ſo it is with all the worldly wiſe, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Whileſt they ſeemed to be wiſe, they became fooles, Rom.</hi> 1.
But marke the wiſedome of <hi>Job,</hi> when he was a Magiſtrate; <hi>When I knew not the
cauſe, I ſought it out diligently, Job</hi> 29.16. This was Gods owne way, to teach man: for
although all things are open and manifeſt to his eyes, yet marke how, in judgement, he commends
deliberation. The ſinnes of Sodome were exceeding grievous, and their Crie was great; yet, <hi>I
will goe downe now</hi> (ſayes God) <hi>and ſee, whether they have done altogether according to
that Crie; and if not, that I may know.</hi> Queſtionleſſe, God heard and knew; but,
<hi>noluit audita judicare,</hi> he would not judge by the eare onely, but by the eye: <hi>Vnus
oculatus teſtis plus valet quam auriti decem,</hi> One ocular witneſſe is worth ten
auricular: therefore he ſaith, <hi>Deſcendam &amp; videbo, I will goe downe and ſee;</hi> to
inſtruct men that are in authoritie. Saith Saint <hi>Gregorie, Magna crimina tardè
credenda ſunt cum audiuntur, citius punienda cum cognoſcuntur;</hi> They muſt be ſlow to
beleeve but upon ſtrong evidence, and readie to puniſh upon juſt proofe. For the Law
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes every man to be good, till he be apparantly bad; but when facts have made the contrarie
evident, then the ſame Law preſumes him to be <hi>ſemper malus qui ſemel malus, in eodem
genere mali,</hi> to be ſtill naught in that kind wherein he is once tainted.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Adam</hi> had ſinned, God proceeded againſt him judiciouſly: Hee came to him, not
running, but <hi>walking;</hi> not in heat, but <hi>coole of the day:</hi> not puniſhing, but
firſt expoſtulating in a voice audible and ſenſible; <hi>Adam, where art thou?</hi> So
<hi>Solomon,</hi> when he heard the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95845:11"/>women ſay what they could, and had ſought out the cauſe diligently, then
<hi>bring me a ſword</hi> (ſaith he); <hi>and all Iſrael heard the judgement which the King
had judged, and they feared the King; for they ſaw that the wiſedome of God was in him, to doe
juſtice,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.28. Wiſdome in the true uſe of the Sword, makes a juſt man
both feared and lov'd; the good men feare him lovingly, the middle ſort love him fearefully:
onely the wicked malefactor feares him ſervilely, <hi>For he beareth not the Sword in
vaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But now, what's Wiſedome without Godlineſſe, but worldly policie?
Therefore to upright judgement Piety is required, The <hi>wiſe man feareth and departeth from
evill,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, Pro.</hi> 14.16. Therefore <hi>when the righteous are in
authority, the people rejoyce; but when the wicked comes on and riſes up, the man is tried, the
good hide themſelves, and the people ſigh, Pro.</hi> 29.2. O how beautifull a ſight it is and
glorious to behold great men to be good men, <hi>Caeſars</hi> favourite to be Chriſts follower!
Religion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore goes beyond Law; for it is but halfe a mans hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to be no better than
the Law makes him, which ſeeth but the out-ſide, and cenſureth onely mens actions: but
Religion cleares the conſcience of evill affections, it reformes the great ones themſelves,
making their eyes ſingle, and eares indifferent, and hands cleane, and hearts upright, to doe
nothing without the teſtimony of a good conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And thirdly, to be religious to God-ward, and not juſt to man, is to be but a
vaine-glorious hypocrite: therefore to the drawing of the <hi>ſword,</hi> which is upright
judgement, Juſtice is a maine requiſite. And it is thus defined by <hi>Vlpianus, Juſtitia
eſt conſtans &amp; perpetua volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas jus ſuum cui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tribuendi.</hi> It is 1.
<hi>voluntas,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95845:12"/>muſt be intended. 2. <hi>conſtans,</hi> therefore ought not to be
corrupted; That's conſtant juſtice, <hi>Quae ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiâ frangi nec pecuniâ
corrumpi, nec gratiâ inflecti poteſt.</hi> Which neither money can wreſt, nor power
breake, nor favour bend. 3. <hi>perpetua,</hi> That ſuppoſeth not one act onely, but an habit;
for juſtice is not to doe <hi>juſta,</hi> which unjuſt men may doe, <hi>Mic.</hi> 6. but
<hi>juſtè,</hi> and that requireth three things, 1. The minde of juſtice in the doer. 2.
The rule of juſtice in the thing done. 3. The end of juſtice in the doing. 4. <hi>Jus ſuum
cui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tribuendi.</hi> To give every man his owne. For as every vertue hath his proper object;
fortitude hath perils, temperance conſiſts in moderation of pleaſures, prudence in politick
affaires, diſcerning good or ill; ſo Juſtice hath <hi>ſuum cuique</hi> for it's object and
office. Of all vertues they ſay Juſtice minds <hi>alienum bonum,</hi> the good of another,
receives no benefit from men, but the praiſe of a juſt action, their prayers and praiſes. And
that juſtly. For if the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate take himſelfe from his buiſineſſe, his friends, and
pleaſures, to intereſt himſelfe in many thankleſſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, to compound idle ſtrifes,
to watch over our ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to be diſturb'd with out-cries when wee ſleepe, is it not juſt
hee ſhould be honoured with an anſwerable eſtate of pomp and magnificence to expreſſe his
great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and this honour be it what it may be, is not <hi>huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis officium,</hi> but
<hi>adminiſtrationis beneficium;</hi> not at our courteſie, but Gods appointment, <hi>For hee
beareth not the ſword in vaine.</hi> And thus you ſee the Sword drawne, which is upright
judgement.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Juſt execution, and that ſtrikes the ſtroke, without which all the reſt
is but an idle flouriſh. In execution of Juſtice, there ought to be a moderation to qualifie
the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95845:12"/>rigour of it; for extremity to be uſed alwayes is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by God
himſelfe. <hi>Noli eſſe juſtus nimis, Eccl.</hi> 7.18. Preſſe not juſtice too farre,
neither urge it extreamely. <hi>Lex enim quia ſeipſam mollire non poteſt, à nobis
mitiganda eſt, ut ſint qui proficiant. Aug.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of
ſome <hi>that turned judgement into gall, and the fruit of righteouſneſſe into wormewood,
Amos</hi> 6.12. There is a Court in <hi>France</hi> called the <hi>Torneilles,</hi> which is the
chamber for criminall cauſes, ſo called becauſe the Judges of the other ſix chambers which
are for civill cauſes, ſit there by turnes; the reaſon <hi>Bodin</hi> gives (as a learned
Surveyer of <hi>France</hi> ſaith) that it might not alter the naturall inclination of the
Judges, and make them more cruell, by being alwayes exerciſed in matters of condemnations and
executions. It was appointed in the law of God, that <hi>forty ſtripes</hi> ſhould be given to
the offender, <hi>and not to exceed, leſt thy brother ſhould be deſpiſed in thy ſight,
Deut.</hi> 25.3. Therefore the Jewes inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Paul fourty ſtripes ſave one.</hi>
Fourty was the law, and if they had given the <hi>ſummum jus</hi> of the law, they thought they
had done injurie; ſo eaſie it is by a tranſpoſition of one letter to turne <hi>Jus</hi>
into <hi>Vis.</hi> There ought to be therefore a wiſe mixture of juſtice and mercy; this
without that, is fooliſh pitie; and that without this, is cruelty. The love of mercie doth not
take away the exerciſe, but ſeverity of juſtice, the acerbity or worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood of it, when the
mighty <hi>hunt their brother with a net, Mic.</hi> 7.2. <hi>or digge pits</hi> (which we call
plots) <hi>for the ſoules of others, Jer.</hi> 18. They doe not think the cup of juſtice bitter
enough, unleſſe it be mingled with their gall.</p>
            <p>The breſt of the Judge ſhould be like the Arke of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95845:13"/>Covenant, wherein three things were put, <hi>Virga, Manna, Tabulae;</hi> the
Tables of the Law, the Rod of <hi>Aaron,</hi> the Pot of Manna; Inſtruction, Unction,
Conſolation. Two things (ſaith <hi>Nazienzene</hi>) are requiſite in Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Lenitie and Severitie; but they both
tranſgreſſe, if not well qualified: if the one be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the other
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, implacable or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet, they may doe much hurt; that looſeth the
reines, with too much remiſſeneſſe; and this ſtrangleth, with too much ſtraitneſſe:
There muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as well as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; humane compaſsion, as well
as ſevere in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation; and then ſtrike on Gods name.</p>
            <p>And now the <hi>Sword</hi> is in your hand, it were good ſome felt the edge of it. Againſt
whom then would you turne it? There are a ſort of Emiſſaries, the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries of Sedition,
that doe ſo ply our Recuſants, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printing in them a ſetled deteſtation of our Church, whom
the Pope having fed a few yeares, makes them his inſtruments to build up his Monarchie: And
hither they come, being bound by a blind obedience, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his pompe with the expence of
their deareſt lives, and are packt over by that relentleſſe Merchant, that trades on no other
but the Red Sea of Blood. Should theſe have the <hi>Sword</hi> turn'd upon them? Some perhaps may
thinke ſo; the <hi>Sword</hi> of Juſtice, not Violence; and ſo thinke I: or rather, if it may
be, I wiſh them all ſound-hearted in England, or ſafe harboured in Rome.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, if any Rebels or ſeditious perſons diſturbe the State, Time, the Mother of
Truth, will diſcover them: The <hi>Sword</hi> is an edged toole; and for me, it is not ſafe
medling with it: God guide the heart and hand of him that beares it. I will be no
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95845:13"/>
               <hi>Bickri,</hi> to blow the Trumpet. The Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth are like
<hi>Hippocrates</hi> Twinnes; they laugh and weepe together, they live and die together: and as the
rending of the Veile of the Temple preſaged the ruine of the ſtate of the Jewes, which followed
ſhortly after; ſo Schiſmes, if not prevented, will overthrow Government, and at laſt bring
in Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie and confuſion. <hi>I would</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that they were cut off
that trouble you, Gal.</hi> 5.12. I dare not wiſh ſo. <hi>Paul</hi> was of an extraordinarie
ſpirit; and the reaſon why I dare not, is, becauſe when a member is cut off, it is hard
ſetting of it on againe. If it be rotten and uncurable, there is need of an <hi>Enſe
reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum eſt.</hi> But, I hope, there is onely a diſlocation, a putting out of joynt; and no
more is required, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a ſetting things right: and that will be beſt done
(ſaith the Apoſtle) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the ſpirit of meekeneſſe, Gal.</hi> 6.1.
<hi>You that are ſpirituall,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, reſtore ſuch: And you that are
temporall Magiſtrates, and beare the <hi>Sword;</hi> you eſpecially. For what can we doe
without you? What can <hi>Aaron</hi> doe without <hi>Moſes? Aaron</hi> may talke, but
<hi>Moſes</hi> with his Rod muſt worke wonders. Wee are compared to the <hi>Teeth</hi> of the
Church, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4. and ſo are you: but wee are onely <hi>Dentes Articulati,</hi> that
forme the Voice; but you are <hi>Dentes Molares,</hi> the Grinders: thoſe whom we cannot reforme
by Preaching, you muſt with your Authoritie breake them.</p>
            <p>Thus ye have heard what belongeth to a Magiſtrate; his Honour, and his Charge. His Honour
ſtands in two things; His Ordinance, his Preeminence: His Charge in the uſe of the
<hi>Sword,</hi> whereunto three things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95845:14"/>1. Good lawes, a <hi>Sword</hi> in the ſcabbard. 2. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right judgement
according to thoſe lawes, a <hi>Sword</hi> drawne. 3. Juſt execution, and that ſtrikes the
ſtroke; <hi>For he beareth not the Sword in vaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, for a concluſion of all, You whom God hath ſo highly honoured; when yee ſee your
ſelves environed with Officers to attend your perſons, your ſeat of Juſtice like a throne
to exalt your Honours, a number of innocent hearers and lookers on to applaud your truth, a
companie of guilty offenders holding up their hands at Barre to expect your Sentence: O then
remember another day of Doome, another ſupreme Judge, before whom hearts ſhall ſpeake, and
tongues ſhall be ſilent, and a good conſcience ſhall be better than a full purſe, At that
day, and before that Judge, whoſe latitude is charity, whoſe longitude aeternity, whoſe depth
inſcrutable wiſedome, and whoſe height incomparable glory. To this Lord in the Trinity of of
perſons, and unity of ſubſtance, One God, Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, be given all
glory, praiſe and power for evermore.</p>
            <p>AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:95845:14"/>
            <p>Perlegi Concionem hanc, dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> judico quae typis man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO. WYKES <hi>R. P. Epiſc. Lond. Sacellanus domeſticus.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
